Jacqueline Van Voris Papers, 1944-1987
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Jacqueline Van Voris papers
1944-1987
Van Voris, Jacqueline
MS 166
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Biographer and Historian. This small collection primarily contains reseach materials for Van Voris's books. Included are audio tapes and transcripts of oral history interviews conducted with Mildred Adams Kenyon, Mary Gray Peck Koehler, Mildred Scott Olmstead, Alice Loomis Clayton, and Louisa K. Fast, some with related correspondence and other materials, such as photographs of suffragist Carrie Chapman Catt. Also included is Van Voris's typed, unpublished manuscript "Quiet Victory: The Waves in World War II" ans associated research interviews.
Jacqueline Van Voris was born to Victor and Genevieve Naggiar in Corsicana, Texas on November 11, 1922. She grew up in Arcata, California. During World War II, she instructed pilots on instrument flying as a Link Trainer with the WAVES for the U.S. Navy from 1944 to 1946. Van Voris received a BA in English from the University of California at Berkeley in 1948. In 1949 she married William Hoover Van Voris. They had two children, Alice Sessions and Richard. She received a Masters in education from Smith College in 1975, and later worked in various capacities for Smith College, including as an interviewer for admissions. She was the author of The Committee of Correspondence: Women with a World Vision and The Look of Paradise: A Pictorial History of Northampton, Massachusetts. She also wrote two biographies, Carrie Chapman Catt: A Public Life and Constance de Markievicz. College: A Smith Mosaic, was the result of interviews with alumnae for the Smith Centennial in 1977. She was also active as publications chair in the Northampton League of Women Voters. Van Voris died on January 29, 2010, at her winter home in Austin, Texas.
The Jacqueline Van Voris Papers consists of research materials for her unpublished manuscript "Quiet Victory: The WAVES in World War II," and for her published biography of Carrie Chapman Catt. Materials on the WAVES include correspondence, interview notes, and a typescript of the book. Materials on Carrie Chapman Catt include correspondence, tapes, and transcripts of interviews conducted circa 1974-1979 with Mildred Adams Kenyon, Mary Gray Peck Koehler, Mildred Scott Olmstead, Alice Loomis Clayton, Louisa K. Fast, and Mrs. J. G. Kellum. Many interviews were conducted with the help of Eleanor Flexner, and some of the correspondence is addressed to her. There are also photographs of suffragist Carrie Chapman Catt, primarily copies from the Iowa History Archives.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
The Jacqueline Van Voris Papers were donated by Van Voris to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 1989.
Search Terms
Adams, Mildred, 1894-; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947; Clayton, Alice Loomis; Fast, Louisa K.; Olmsted, Mildred Scott, 1890-1990; Peck, Mary Gray; Van Voris, Jacqueline; United States. Naval Reserve. Women's Reserve--History--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Women historians--United States--Biography--Sources; Women--Biography--Sources; Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
The Smith College Archives contain the records of the Smith Centennial Study Oral History Project, including complete transcripts, as well as a copy of College: A Smith Mosaic. Neilson Library holds copies of Van Voris' other works. The Sophia Smith Collection contains a number of oral histories conducted by Van Voris in various collections, including the Dorothea De Schweinitz and Louise De Schweinitz (Darrow) Papers, the Katharine Edith Brand Papers, the Elmina Rose Lucke Papers, the Margaret Sanger Papers, the Jessie Lloyd O'Connor Papers, and the Gloria Steinem Papers, and the Committeee of Correspondence Records.
- Carrie Chapman Catt: A Public Life
  - Alice Loomis Clayton: transcript, 11 May 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Louisa K. Fast: transcript, correspondence with Eleanor Flexner, audio recording, printed material, 1971-74 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. J. G. Kellum: interview notes, 13 Mar 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mildred Adams Kenyon: transcript, audio recording, correspondence, and photos, 1974-75, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mary Gray Peck Koehler: transcript, audio recording, 11 Aug 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mildred Scott Olmstead: transcript, correspondence, and audio recording, 1976-79 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Carrie Chapman Catt and her homes, circa 1885-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Quiet Victory: The Waves in World War II"
  - "Quiet Victory: The Waves in World War II," typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Author comments and interview notes, 1968-75, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence
    - Rita Lenihan, Mar 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Antha Card, 1944-68 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dorothy Council, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)